Guide to the Robert Schmertz Collection, 1898-2001 CAM.SCHM.2015
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Poems, V.
  - Poems (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - Christopher Robin Goes in for Some Post-War Planning (with apologies to Mr. Milne) (Box 4, Item 125.3)
      Typed manuscript on onion-skin. 1 page.
    - Decentralize Organically with Me (Box 4, Item 125.31)
    - Lament, April 1955 (Box 4, Item 125.32)
      Tear sheet from the Journal of the A.I.A. 4 pages.
    - Ode to the Ladies of the Oldest Book Club in America with Love from Robert W. Schmertz (Box 4, Item 125.33)
      mimeographed poem. 1 page
    - Ode to the Ladies by Robert W. Schmertz with Apologies to William Butler Yates (sic) On the Occasion of the Book Club Meeting, March 15, 1958 (Box 4, Item 125.34)
      mimeographed poem. 1 page.
    - The King and the Trumpeter (Box 4, Item 125.35)
      Typed manuscript with handwritten music notation. two pages. Stapled.
    - Idle Thoughts on a Florentine Excursion (with a sore foot) (Box 4, Item 125.36)
      Handwritten manuscript with illustrations. 3 pages. 2 photocopies. all attached with paperclip.
    - [Oh Mister Horowitz, Oh Mister Horowitz] (Box 4, Item 125.37)
    - On the Closing of the Anderson Hotel (Box 4, Item 125.38)
      handwritten manuscript on lined yellow paper. Two pages.
    - To an Unpublished Poet (Box 4, Item 125.39)
      Handwritten manuscript on lined yellow legal sized paper. 1 page.
    - The Underground Zoo (Box 4, Item 125.4)
      copy of typed manuscript. Two pages. Stapled.
    - Come to the Hills of West Virginia (Box 4, Item 125.41)
      Clipping of published poem from unnamed publication. 1 page.
    - Ode to the Ladies of the Oldest Book Club in American with Love from Robert C. Schmertz (Box 4, Item 125.42)
      typed manuscript with handwritten notes. 1 page.
    - The Palazzo was Pushed (Box 4, Item 125.43)
      Illustrated poem published in The Charette. Date unknown. One handwritten correction.
    - Ode to the Lally Column (Swing Version) (Box 4, Item 125.44)
      Published poem in The Charette (no date known). 1 page.
    - To George Howe (Box 4, Item 125.45)
    - Cliffy or Pappy Dunnells, April 16, 1943 (Box 4, Item 125.46)
      Typed manuscript on onion skin. 1 page.
    - [said Christopher Wren to Christopher Robin] (Box 4, Item 125.47)
      handwritten manuscript marked on small yellow paper. 4 pages.
    - [Here's another Christmas] (Box 5, Folder 165)
      handwritten poem on lined paper. 1 page.
    - [animal poems] (Box 5, Folder 166)
      16 handwritten poems about animals on lined paper. 4 pages. Typed manuscript of 7 of the poems. 4 copies.
- Plays, VI.
  This series contains play manuscripts written by Robert Schmertz.
  - [untitled play] (Box 4, Folder 124)
    bound, typed play manuscript with handwritten corrections. Unnumbered pages.
  - The Mermaid in Lock No. 7 a short musical play, May 14, 1958 (Box 4, Item 123)
    Typed bound manuscript. Music by Elie Siegmeister. Book and lyrics by Edward Mabley.
- Photographs, VII.
  This series contains photographs of Robert Schmertz and others.
  - Schmertz College Combo Carnegie Tech, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 120)
    black and white photo mounted on black construction paper.
  - Photo of Robert Schmertz with banjo (Box 4, Item 121)
    Photo of Bob Schmertz seated with banjo. 8 x 10.
  - [unidentified photo of group making music in a private home] (Box 4, Item 115)
    group of people seated and standing singing, some playing banjos, guitars, and tambourine.
- Newsclippings, VIII.
  This series contains newspaper clippings of articles about Robert Schmertz, performers who played his music, and other Schmertz family members.
  - Newsclippings (Box 1, Folder 118)
    - Christian, Hebrew Church Art on Display Here, December 20, 1951 (Box 1, Item 118.01)
      newsclipping about Mildred Schmertz design work.
    - Pittsburgh's Minstrel Laureate, 1975 (Box 1, Item 118.02)
      News clipping about Bob Schmertz. No source identified.
    - Pittsburgh's Minstrel Laureate, 1975 (Box 1, Item 118.03)
      Obituary of Robert Schmertz from unnamed paper.
    - Schmertz, 1975 (Box 1, Item 118.04)
      obituary from unnamed paper of Robert Schmertz. 2 copies.
    - Robert W. Schmertz, Architect, Composer, 1975 (Box 1, Item 118.05)
    - Local Medley, Singer Delight Crowd, May 23, 1972 (Box 1, Item 118.07)
      Article from The Pitt News describing an event Schmertz performed at. (2 copies)
    - An Evening of Fun, April 1, 1976 (Box 1, Item 118.08)
      Article by Rex Rutkoski in the Valley News Dispatch describing a benefit to raise money to publish "A Picture Book of songs and Ballads of Robert Schmertz."
    - Seeger, 73, relishes his role as a song leader, May 14, 1992 (Box 1, Item 118.09)
      article about Seeger's performance at the Carnegie Lecture Hall that mentions Bob Schmertz. From The Pittsburgh Press, May 14, 1992.
    - City Singer Schmertz Now Back in Action, May 16, 1972 (Box 1, Item 118.1)
      Article about Schmertz in The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette by Donald Miller (2 copies).
    - Seeger Highlighting Musical Menu (Box 1, Item 118.11)
      Article by Pete Bishop in unnamed paper. Mentions Robert Schmertz.
    - Professor wants students' work to be letter perfect, Feb. 3, 1983 (Box 1, Item 118.12)
      Article from Pittsburgh Post-Gazette. Not clear why it was kept (doesn't mention Schmertz).
    - New Triumph for Schmertz (Box 1, Item 118.13)
      Article by Lester Sullivan about Schmertz's album "Robert Schmertz sings his songs."
    - The troubadour of the two-by-four, June 27, 1975 (Box 1, Item 118.14)
      Article about Schmertz by William Marlin in The Christian Science Monitor.
    - Ruth Etting Story Booked by Penn, May 17, 1955 (Box 1, Item 118.15)
      Article by Karl Krug in Pittsburgh Sun-Telegraph. Unclear why it was retained (no mention of Schmertz)
    - Song-Writing Architect Dies Here at Age 77, June 9, 1975 (Box 1, Item 118.16)
      Obituary in the Pittsburgh Press.
    - Busy Housekeeper Has Many Interests (Box 1, Item 118.17)
      Article about Gretchen Schmertz, Robert's daughter. Written by Mary Irene Moffitt.
    - Architect noted for his wit and song honored, June 1974 (Box 1, Item 118.18)
      article on Schmertz from Architectural Record.
    - Model School (Box 1, Item 118.19)
      Letter to the editor by Margaret Hodges hailing Gretchen Jacobs' leadership at Liberty School.
    - Don't Try to Figure This Out -- It's 'Too Much,', 1950 (Box 1, Item 118.2)
      Article with Photo about the Scotch 'n Soda Club at Carnegie Tech's production, which includes Gretchen Schmertz. In The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette.
    - S 'n S Crews and Writers Wait for Opening Tonight, May 10, 1950 (Box 1, Item 118.21)
      Article about Carnegie Tech's Scotch 'n Soda's production, starring Gretchen Schmertz. Article appears in The Tartan, Carnegie Tech's student paper.
    - Old-Time 'n' Homey, That's Folks Music, May 28, 1981 (Box 1, Item 118.22)
      Article about The 1981 Smoky City Folk Festival that mentions The Friends of Robert Schmertz.
    - Savoyards perform Gilbert & Sullivan with love, October 29, 1982 (Box 1, Item 118.23)
      Article about the Pittsburgh Savoyards, which a number of Schmertz relations are participating in. Written by Gretchen Haller in The Pittsburgh Post-Gazette.
    - Show Shops: Amusement Parade Highlights, January 5, 1956 (Box 1, Item 118.24)
      Article mentions "Noah Found Grace in the Eyes of the Lawd," sung by Gary Crosby, Bing Crosby's son. Article by Kaspar Monahan in The Pittsburgh Press.
    - Robert Schmertz Sings, November 1955 (Box 1, Item 118.25)
      profile of Robert Schmertz's album "Robert Schmertz Sings His Songs" from Pittsburgh Magazine.
    - Pete Seeger Folk singer views the future: 'We must change our thinking or there'll be no human race,', August 16, 1975 (Box 1, Item 118.26)
      Article about Seeger in The Valley News Dispatch by Rex Rutkoski.
- Songbooks, IX.
  This series contains published songbooks that include Schmertz songs.
  - 22 Favorite Folk Songs, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 169)
    Edited and arranged by Richard C. Pisano. Published by Hollis Music, Inc. 38 pages.
    Contents: Alouette; Barbara Allen; Bury me Not on the Lone Prairie; Git on Board, Little Children (The Gospel Train's A Comin'); Goodnight, Irene; I Ain't Goin' Study War No More (Down By the Riverside); If I Had a Hammer (The Hammer Song); Jesse James; Michael, Row the Boat Shore; Noah Found Grace in the Eyes of the Lord; On Top of Old Smoky; Pick a Bale O' Cotton; Red River Valley; Sally, Don't You Grieve; Shenandoah; So Long (It's Been Good to Know Yuh); Sweet Betsy From Pike; This Land is Your Land; Tom Dooley; Vive L'Amour; Were You There?
  - Carnegie Song Book, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 171)
    Compiled and edited by Alfred H. Johnson and members of the Carnegie Tartan Staff. Handwritten notation on the fly leaf that this was Robert Schmertz's personal copy.
    contents:
    New Alma Mater; Women's Song; Carnegie Tech; Lau Carnegie; Amici; Glory of the Plaid; Sing Praises to Alma Mater; Dear Old Tech; Fight for the Glory of Carnegie; Cheer Song; On the Warpath; Sing the Praises; Hail to Carnegie; Si McNadd; Tech, Tech, Tech, Tech; I Love an Engineer; Come on Along to tech; Nile Song; Eskimo Baby; Hieroglyphic Ditty; Whimsical Women; Ship Ahoy; Love's Waltz; Moonlight Maid; Any Old Place at All; In Barcelona Wedding Bells; Yells
  - The Folk Singers Song Bag Volume 2, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 172)
    21 songs with words and guitar chords. A Publication of Sanga Music Inc.
    Contents: When the Stars Begin to Fall; A Man Come Into Egypt; I'm Standing on the Outside of Your Shelter; Who's Gonna Be Your Man; The Ladybug and the Centipede; Full Fathom Five; East Texas; Red Ram of Darby; Take Matty and Go; Monongahela Sal; On My Journey; Juanita; Cuddlebug; Coorie Doon; The Bells Ring Over Erin; Bright Golden Buttons; Guilford Fair; To the Year That's Away; Motherless Childen (sic); Skillet; Long About Now
  - A Picture Book of Songs & Ballads Composed and Illustrated by Robert Schmertz, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 174)
    5 copies. Edited by Jo Davidson. Arranged by Lee B. Thomssen.
    contents: Biographical Sketch of Robert W. Schmertz; Notes on the Transcriber-Arranger and Editor; "Eine Kleine Nactmusik, or My Musical Heritage" by Robert W. Schmertz; Monongahela Sal; Lock Number Ten; Lorenzo; II Magnifico; The Palazzo Massimi; Hyacinth Harry; Nellie of Meadow Farm; The Rambling River Line; Jose (Hozay) the Horse; The Folks of the Ohio; Angus MacFergus MacTavish Dundee; Christmas Song for Gretchen; The Lonely Grenadier; Cousin Althalia; Mon Petit Lapin; Never Touch Water; The Knight of Small Reknown; Lord, Lord I've Got Some Singing to Do; Gideon Bible; My Baby Eskimo; Forty-Nine Angels; The Queen Anne Front (and the Mary Ann Behind); "The Biggest Living Room in Town; Bob Schmertz Sings" by Gretchen Haller Pearson; Production Notes by Richard F. Myers, Buzzard's Knob Associates
- Sound Recordings, X.
  This series contains sound recordings on LP, 78, and CD of Schmertz's songs.
  - Put that Horn Down Gabriel and Foxy was a Fox (Box 6, Record 183)
    33 1/3 rpm record. 1 song on each side. No music label or publication information.
  - Noah Found Grace in the Eyes of the Lord and Dry Bones (Box 6, Record 184)
    45 rpm disc with one song on each side. Performed by Steel City Four. Recorded by George Heid Productions, Pittsburgh. Corona Records. GHP475A & B
  - Noah and Every Time I Feel the Spirit (Box 6, Record 185)
    45 rpm disc. 1 song on each side. Performed by Bruce Low and Orchester Charles Nowa. Ariola Records. C 10407A & B.
  - Monongahela Sal (and other ballads), 1972 (Box 6, Record 186)
    33 1/3 disc. Two songs on each side. Sung and played by Robert Schmertz, Vivien Richman, Charles Cabulic, Anne Shapiro, Jack Schmertz, Gretchen Schmertz-Jacob, and Jo Davidson. Master Artists Recordings, 1972. 4385A & B. 3 copies, one not in a sleeve.
  - Monongahela Sal; Parking Space; Gideon Bible; Parking space (Box 6, Record 187)
    Unlabeled record. Title written on manila envelope from Varbee Records.
  - Bongo and His Baboon Drum and Quack, Quack, Paddle - Oh! (Box 6, Record 188)
    45 rpm disc. Two Sides. Performed by Burl Ives. Decca children's series, Record No. 9-88167 (45-86056)
  - Noah Found Grace in the Eyes of the Lord and Get a Load O' Me (Box 6, Record 189)
    45 rpm disc. Two sides. Performed by Gary Crosby with Orchestra directed by Buddy Bregman. Decca Records. Record No. 9-29779 (L-8652)
  - Angus McFergus MacTavish Dundee and The Tenor Doodle-Doo (Box 6, Record 190)
    2 sides. Performed by Burl Ives. Decca Children's Series, 88867 (88208).
  - Songs by Robert Schmertz, 1949 (Box 6, Record 191)
    3 album set. Composed by Robert Schmertz. Recorded by George Heid Productions, Pittsburgh, PA. S100, 101, and 102. (2 sets)
    Contents:
    The Queen Anne Front and the Mary Anne Behind Noah Found Grace in the Eyes of the Lord Nellie of Meadow Farm Spring on the Campus Palazzo Massimi Monongahela Sal
  - Dangerous Songs!? (Box 6, Record 192)
    33 1/3 record. Performed by Pete Seeger. Columbia Records CL2503.
    Contents: Medley: Robin the Bobbie; Mary, Mary quite contrary; Little Jack Horner; Die Gedanken sind Frei (Thoughts are Free); Jackaro; Never Wed an Old Man; John Brown's Body; Going Across the Mountains; Harry Simms; King Henry Medley: Ode to Joy; Goliath, Goliath; Queen Anne Front; Joe Hill's "Casey Jones"; One Grain of Sand; The Pill; The Draft Dodger Rag; Mao Tse Tung; Walking Down Death Row; Two from Shakespeare: Full Fathom Five/ Perchance to Win; Beans in my Ears
  - Vivien Richman Sings Folk songs "For You and Me", 1960 (Box 6, Record 193)
    33 1/3 disc. Jersey City: Bobtone Rcord and Tape Co. FLP 2066
    Contents: I'm Gonna Live the Life I Sing About; When I First Came to This Land; The Queen Anne Front; Nine Hundred Miles; The Lost Ballad of Wiscasset; Freedom Songs; This Land is Your Land; Cindy Hora Banechar; All the Pretty Little Horses; Layla, Layla; Whistle, Daughter, Whistle; Jamele, Jamele; Finjan; Oh, What a Beautiful City
  - Vivien Richman Sings Folk songs of West Pennsylvania (Box 6, Record 194)
    33 /13 Record. Folkways Records FG 3568. Autographed by Vivien Richman
    The Glooms of Ligonier; The Forks of the Ohio; Sinclaire's Defeat; The Mouse's Courting Song; James Bird; The Conestoga Wagoner's Complaint; The Hero of Erie; The Jolly Lumbermen; Hold on; Aja Lejber Man; A Still Mill Tragedy; "Pittsburgh" Hymn; I'm a Beggar; Red Iron Ore; Handsome Mary, the Lily of the West; The Twenty-inch Mill; Soho on Saturday Night; Pittsburgh Town
  - Robert Schmertz Sings his Songs, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 195)
    Record sleeve only. Album missing.
  - Sing oh! the City oh! (Box 6, Folder 196)
    Record sleeve only. Record is missing.
  - 78 rpm Tracks (Box 6, Disc 197)
    CD. Performed by Robert Schmertz. No track list.
  - Robert Schmertz Sings His Songs (Box 6, Disc 198)
    CD transfer of album.
  - 33 rpm Tracks (Box 6, Disc 199)
    CD transfer of Schmertz 33 rpm discs. No contents listed.
  - Vivien Richman Sings Folk Songs of West Pennsylvania (Box 6, Disc 200)
    CD transfer of folkways 03568.
  - Sing Oh! The City Oh! (Box 6, Disc 201)
    CD Transfer of Folkways 05258
  - Robert Schmertz Sings his songs (Box 6, Disc 202)
    CD Transfer of Robert Schmertz Sings His Sons.
  - Ladies Beware of an Architect: Songs for Architects and their Girl Friends, 1960 (Box 6, Disc 203)
    CD transfer of original recording.
    Nellie of Meadow Farm; The Palazzo Massimi; Lorenzo il Magnifico; Spring on the Campus; Hyacinth Harry; When That Architect Comes to Jordan; When I Was a Young Nouveau; The Queen Anne Front; The Doric Column is Coming Back; Walter and Mies and Corbu; John Lally of Boston Baby; I Don't See Eye to Eye; The Old White Bones of Christopher Wren
  - [untitled "takes that are good"] (Box 6, Reel 7, Folder 205)
    BASF Reel to Reel tape. #4385
  - Songs for and About Men (Box 7, Record 206)
    33 1/3 rpm disc. Performed by Burl Ives. Decca Records DL 8125.
    Contents: The Locktender's Lament; Ox Driver's Song; The Bold Soldier; The Young Married Man (Cod Liver Oil); Sad man's song (Fare Thee Well, O Honey); The Harlem Man; The Western Settler; Waltzing Matilda (The Jolly Swagman's Song); The Wild Rover; Frankie and Johnny; The Deceiver (Oh, How He Lied); The Sailor's Return; When I was Single; Prisoner's Song (Midnight Special); John Henry
  - Walt Disney Present Burl Ives Folk Lullabies, 1964 (Box 7, Record 207)
    33 1/3 rpm album with full color book and words. ST 3924
    The Moon's the North Wind's Cookie; Little Lost Angel; What Are Little Boys Made Of?; All Through the Night; Indian Lullaby; Cradle Song; Lady Moon; Sweet and Low; Punkydoodle and Jollapin; Goodnight Sweet Dreams; Tom, the Piper's Son; Sleep and Rest
  - Holy Bible Old Testament, 1975 (Box 7, Record 208)
    Recorded by the Statler Brothers. Mercury Records SRM-1-1051.
    In the Beginning; Even Noah Found Grace in the Eyes of the Lord; Have a Little Faith; The Dreamer; Led Out of Bondage; The ten Commandments; Samson; Song of David; Song of Solomon; The Fourth Man; The King is Coming
  - We've Got Some Singing to Do, 1958 (Box 7, Record 209)
    33 1/3 record. Performed by the Folksmiths. Folkways Records, 1958. FA2407
    Lord, I've Got Some Singing to Do; Hava Na Shira; John Henry; Old Hannah; Glory Be to the New-Born King; Come Up Horsey; Three White Gulls; Mary Had a Baby; Sinner Man; Blood-Strained Banders Hold On (Keep Your Hand on the Plow); Kum Ba Yah; Wade in the Water; Run to Jesus; Hey Langor; Tina; All Night Long
  - Folk Songs for a Coffee House (Box 7, Record 210)
    33 1/3 Record. Performed by Ron and Jane Salof. Bobton Record and Tape Co. FLP 2060
    The Fire Ship; Proschay; Black is the Color; Four Nights; Drunk Dodi-Li; Greensleeves; Knight of Small Renown; Rolling Down the Mountain; As I Rode; Out Sur Le Route; Birds counting song; All the Pretty Little Horses; E Doce Morrer; Monongahela Sal; Spinster's Lament
  - Come Home It's Suppertime (Box 7, Record 211)
    33 1/3 record. Performed by The Humbards. Cincinnati: Rite Record Productions.
    Suppertime; Noah Found Grace; Jesus, Wonderful Lord; Gathering Home; I'm Going Higher; When the Saints Go Marching; Wasted Years; Shadrack; Like a Melody; I Shall Not be Moved; Down From his Glory; I Will Not Be a Stranger; I've Found a Hiding Place; You Ain't Got Nuthin; He'll Understand and Say Well Done
  - Tennessee Ernie Ford Spirituals (Box 7, Record 212)
    33 1/3 Record. Capitol Records T818.
    Just a Closer Walk with Thee; I Want to Be Ready; Take My Hand, Precious Lord; Stand by Me; When God Dips His Love in my Heart; Get on Board, Little Children; Noah Found Grace in the Eyes of the Lord; Were You There?; Peace in the Valley; I Know the Lord Laid his Hands on Me; Wayfaring Pilgrim; He'll Understand and Say "Well Done"
  - Sing oh! The City oh!, 1959 (Box 7, Record 213)
    Subtitle: Songs about early Pittsburgh by Robert Schmertz with Vivien Richman, Gretchen Schmertz Jacob, Eero Davidson, John Schmertz
    Folkways Records FA 5258
    Sing Oh, the City Oh!; Celeron Ohio Company; Forks of the Ohio; La Vierge Mon Petit Lapin; Braddock's Defeat; General John Forbes; The Lonely Grenadier; Flintlock Finegan; The Battle of Bushy Run; Prettiest Girl in Pittsburgh Town
- Miscellaneous, XI.
  This series contains miscellaneous items that didn't fit into the other series categories.
  - Apple Ternover (Box 2, Folder 119)
    Acrylic painting
  - [song list] (Box 5, Folder 163)
    list of songs or acts handwritten on card stock.